BU Records: Aerospace Studies Department, Inclusive: 1942-1973, undated, Bulk: 1965-1973
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Aerospace Studies Department
Inclusive: 1942-1973, undated, Bulk: 1965-1973
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/5
Baylor University
5 document boxes and 1 oversized box
BU Records: Aerospace Studies Department consists of correspondence, scrapbooks, photographic material, and literary productions produced by the Baylor University Aerospace Studies Department, a University-sponsored military preparation program in partnership with the U.S. Air Force.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Baylor University's Aerospace Studies Department was founded in July 1948 as a partnership between the United States Air Force and Baylor University, making it one of the first founded after the establishment of the Air Force as a separate branch of the military. The department is in charge of the Baylor University Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corps (AFROTC) program. Air Force ROTC Detachment 810 is still in operation today.
Scope and Content
This collection begins in 1942 and ends in 1973. The materials provide a window into the daily operations of the Baylor Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corps and documents the exploits of its cadets. The series include correspondence (primarily orders from the group commanders to the department,) scrapbooks, photographic material, literary productions (primarily comprised of textbooks and student newsletters,) and clippings. The greatest concentration of material is from the latter half of the 1960s and the first four years of the 1970s.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, this collection was not arranged in any particular order. Currently, the collection is organized in four series separated by material type and ordered chronologically within those series: I. Correspondence, II. Scrapbooks, III. Photographic Material, and IV. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/5. Acquired 1975-03-26
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History, Military.; United States. Air Force.
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- History -- 20th Century.
Subjects
Military education -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Albums (Books); Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Textbooks.
- Correspondence, 1948-1972; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consist primarily of correspondence between the Aerospace Studies Department administration and cadets. The bulk is made up of daily orders and special orders. Of note is the folder of materials prepared for the visit of Air Force Brigadier General Daniel "Chappie" James to Waco in 1972.
  - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1948-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Daily Orders, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Operation Orders, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Special Orders, 1948-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Special Orders, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reserve Orders, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brigadier General Daniel “Chappie” James, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Scrapbooks, 1942-1964; 2
  This series contains scrapbooks prepared by the department for various graduating classes. They consist primarily of photographs and news clippings. Of particular interest is the 1942-1943 scrapbook, which detailed the exploits of Baylor students in World War II. Although there is no information included, it is likely that it was assembled by one of the officers later assigned to Baylor when the Aerospace Studies Department was founded.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Scrapbook, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook (1 of 5), 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook (2 of 5), 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook (3 of 5), 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook (4 of 5), 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (5 of 5), 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1942-1943 (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (1 of 4), 1963-1964 (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (2 of 4), 1963-1964 (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook (3 of 4), 1963-1964 (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook (4 of 4), 1963-1964 (Box 6 OVZ, Folder 5)
- Photographic Material, 1947-1973; 3
  This series contains photographic material documenting the Aerospace Studies Department’s events. The majority of the material is dedicated to awards ceremonies and parades. Of particular interest are the photographs of the AFROTC Rifle Team (undated).
  Photo negative; Photographic print
  - Photographs (1 of 2), 1952-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (2 of 2), 1952-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (1 of 2), 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (2 of 2), 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs (1 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs (2 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (3 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs (4 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs (5 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs (6 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photographs (7 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (8 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photographs (9 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Literary Productions, 1947-1973; 4
  This series contains literary productions produced by the Aerospace Studies Department, primarily taking the form of textbooks and student newsletters. There is one subseries of newspaper clippings.
  - Catalogue (1 of 4), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Catalogue (2 of 4), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Catalogue (3 of 4), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Catalogue (4 of 4), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Corps Rosters (1 of 2), 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Corps Rosters (2 of 2), 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cadet Regulations (1 of 2), 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cadet Regulations (2 of 2), 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cadet Regulations, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Job Description Guide, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lesson Plans, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Speeches, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Textbook, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Textbook, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Student Handbooks, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Student Handbooks, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Student Handbook, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Student Handbooks, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Yearbook, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - News Releases, 1951-1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - News Releases, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters, 1953-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, 1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Programs and Tickets, 1949-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Blank Forms, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1955-1964 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)